"Parabiosis Experiments Prove
Bloodborne Aging Factors"
One of the major hallmarks
of agin
is the decline of regenerative
capacity of our tissues.
There are stem cells residing
in our muscles, for example,
that can leap into service
at the first sign of injury
to repair any damage.
Is the waning
of tissue renewing abilities
due to some intrinsic property
of aging stem cells
or a consequence of being
trapped in an aging body?
To find out, researchers grafted
the muscles of old rats
into young rats and vice-versa.
Inside the young rat,
even the weak atrophied muscles
of extremely old rats
at the end of their lives
regained their strength, volume,
and ability to regenerate.
They became young again,
so the capacity
was still there all along.
And young muscles in old rats
lost renewal capacity,
so it appeared to be something
about the surrounding milieu
rather than
inherent defects with age.
To see if the critical elements
were circulating
in the bloodstream,
old muscle stem cells
were cultured
in the blood of young animals.
This alone had
a rejuvenating effect,
suggesting that there may be
some sort of vitalizing factors
in youth that we lose as we age,
or inversely,
some repair-repressing component
that builds up.
Either way,
this may be good news,
because if we can find out
what those factors are,
we may be able to slow aging
or even reverse it.
Could more than just muscle
be restored?
What about the brain
and all the other organs?
To see the extent in which
circulating factors might play
in affecting aging,
researchers turned
to a macabre procedure
called parabiosis, from the
Greek para, meaning "next to,"
and bios, for "life."
It was an attempt
to recreate the phenomenon
of conjoined twins in a lab
by sewing animals together
to study the effects
of transmissible factors.
Conjoined twins are often
referred to as "Siamese twins,"
due to the notoriety of a 19th
century pair of Siamese-American
brothers joined at the chest.
The Blazek sisters are the
only conjoined twins on record
ever having given birth.
Josepha and Rosa Blazek
were quite literally
joined at the hip.
When Rosa got pregnant,
both of their breasts developed
and started lactating,
supporting the theory
we now know to be true today
that lactation is
regulated by hormones
that circulate in the blood.
So what about aging factors
circulating in the blood?
Surgically, researchers can
connect the skin, circulation,
muscle walls, body cavities,
and shoulder blade joints
of two animals.
Early attempts to graft
different species failed--
for example, mammals to birds
or a cat to a rat,
but in 1862,
a pioneering French scientist
was able to successfully pair
together two young rats.
The first heterochronic union--
hetero meaning "different,"
Chronos meaning "time"--
the first heterochronic union
was created in 1955
to answer the question:
What would happen if you bathed
the tissues of an old animal
in the blood of a young one?
The title of the paper was,
"Experimental Prolongation
of the Life Span."
Old rats hooked up to young rats
lived about 20 percent longer
than old rats
hooked up to one another.
Subsequent experiments showed
old mice coupled with young
became healthier, stronger,
and smarter.
Aged tissues in a number
of organs were rejuvenated,
including the brain, heart,
pancreas, skeleton, and muscles.
That doesn't necessarily mean
that aging was slowed, though.
Rather than some sort of
restorative bloodborne factor,
maybe the older animals
were just taking advantage
of the reserve organ capacity
in the younger animals,
like having an extra set
of youthful kidneys.
To see whether there's
some aging or anti-aging
transmissible element,
rather than sharing organs and
an entire circulatory system,
what about just getting
a transfusion of young blood?
After all,
as an American Aging Association
journal review concluded:
"The use of parabiosis in humans
is currently not performed
due to the surgical
complications
and resulting
undesirable lifestyle."
Ya think?
But getting a transfusion
of young blood would be easy.
Does it work?
We'll find out next.